Welcome to The Test Set. Here we talk with some of the brightest thinkers and tinkerers
in statistical analysis, scientific computing, and machine learning. Digging into what makes
them tick, plus the insights, experiments, and OMG moments that shape the field.
On this episode, we talk with Leland McInnes, creator of UMAP, an algorithm that turns high-dimensional
data into something easier to visualize. It's been used all over, from tracing illegally
mined gold, studying solar wind, and even helping artists work with whale song.
Leland joined the Tutte Institute as a pure mathematician, but kept finding interesting
problems on the data science side. He says, I just want to find ways to condense and extract
information to just allow someone to explore a dataset better. We talk about the challenge
of imposter syndrome and interdisciplinary work, his approach to AI, and why he thinks
exploring data depends on human taste and curiosity.
Hey everyone, welcome to The Test Set. We're joined by Leland McInnes, who's a research
mathematician and data scientist at the Tutte Institute for Mathematics and Computing, and
contributed to HDBSCAN and created UMAP, a really interesting and popular algorithm for
clustering and you've probably seen it in a lot of visualization. So, Leland, so happy
to have you on. Thanks for coming on.
Thank you so much for having me. Really appreciate it.
Yeah, and then just by way of introduction, I'm the host, Michael Chow, and I'm joined
by Hadley Wickham, who's chief scientist at Posit, and Wes McKinney, who's a principal
architect at Posit and founder of Kenio AI Computing Tools Company. So, happy to have
everyone together. Do y'all, I'm curious, have y'all met before?
I feel like we've likely crossed paths, maybe at like a Sci-Pi conference or something,
but I'm having a hard time placing it.
Met you at a Sci-Pi, Wes. I obviously remember it because it was a chance for me to meet
one of my heroes. You obviously will not remember it because it was a long time ago and I hadn't
done much by that point.
Yeah, I think the first Sci-Pi that I went to was in 2010. And so, there've been a lot
of years, a lot of conferences, and a lot of alcoholic beverages in between now and
then.
It makes sense though, Sci-Pi. I think Leland, a lot of your tools have been in Python and
you have a lot of implementations of things in Python. Do you go to most of the Sci-Pi
conferences?
I went for many years. I didn't go this year and I missed a few years around COVID. So,
otherwise I try and get there whenever I can. It's a great conference.
I went to Sci-Pi this year, so we could have crossed paths, but I missed out.
I think the joke is Hadley and I are trading places. I think some years he's at a Python
conference, I'm in an R conference. It's happened once or twice. Pigs aren't flying,
I can see, but times have certainly evolved. A great deal is the field of data science
has become more polyglot and the communities are intersecting a lot more.
Yeah, I have not made it to an R conference yet. That's on my list of things to get around
to doing. I do have colleagues that do a lot of R. Python's where I landed, but I'm not wedded.
And you must go to a bunch of academic CS conferences too?
Yeah, math and CS conferences as well.
Yeah, reading about your background and a lot of things you've done,
so interesting where you're kind of straddling pure mathematics and data science.
And I think one thing that really caught me from some of what you said before this interview is
you mentioned when thinking about the downstream impact of your work,
people reaching out sometimes for help or feedback on problems. And I almost wondered
if one way to really kind of introduce people to UMAP and some of this is I saw you mentioned
people reaching out about things even like illegal gold mining. I don't know how much
you can say about that, but I'd be curious how people are using things like UMAP.
So this is one of those things where I know nothing about the subject matter and
I got someone reached out for a little advice and just consultation on using UMAP within this
framework, but it was about managing to identify gold samples that had come from locations where
there were not supposed to be mining and they try and I'm going to get all the details probably
wrong, but I'll get the gist of it right. They were essentially trying to mix it in with other
gold. So it just gets laundered into the general supply, but there are like impurities in gold
that can be traced back and so for just managing to pull out clusters and structure in this sort of
analysis of the trace minerals in gold, UMAP was one of the tools that got used in that and
they were just wanting to clarify some things on that, but this is not a field I would
have expected to see it used in and so it's just really interesting to see the different ways that
these tools actually get used in practice to solve real world problems.
If I understand what you're saying is sort of like they have a lot of samples and they can take a lot
of measurements on the gold and that sort of makes it a really high dimensional problem, like each
measurement is kind of a dimension and they kind of want to break it down to cluster
all the observations to say like what are these groupings and maybe one of these groupings is sort
of like the illegally mined gold, is that?
Yeah, that's my understanding. It's been a while, but it was an interesting use case. There are a lot of
very strange little use cases like that that crop up and I unfortunately am unable to keep up with the
sort of subject matter specifics, so all I have is the rough idea. But yeah,
I mean it's been used in astronomy for something to do with identifying things in solar wind.
Again, I'm not an expert in astronomy and I can't comment on the specifics, but it's just
intriguing to see the kinds of use cases that crop up.
It's super interesting where you're kind of dipping into different areas and
almost like playing in everyone's backyard a little bit.
Yeah, I've had to try and desperately quickly learn various different subjects as they come up.
I'm never going to be an expert in it, but I've had to learn more biology than I ever wanted to
know because UMAP gets used a lot in various fields in biosciences and that is 100% not my
field. But it comes up often enough that I think I have had to try and learn as much as I can to at
least give vaguely reasonable advice if people ask questions.
Yeah, I'm really curious. I know you also mentioned you studied math and then after
your master's you were working in a casino a lot. It seems like you've done a lot of this sort of
pure math to data science. I'm really curious almost to give people a sense of kind of how
you got into all this. If you could run us through a bit of your background and how you
got to the casino and where you went from there. Yeah, so I went through an accelerated program
at university that kind of put me through undergrad and then master's in a somewhat
more compressed program. I started out actually in physics but ended up just being pure math by
the end. So my master's was in algorithms in algebraic geometry. But by that point I was
kind of burned out on academia to be honest because it had been a pretty intense environment.
So I decided to just try doing something else. So I looked around and there was a company that
was hiring mathematicians which you know doesn't happen that often. So I applied there and that
was a company that turned out they specialized in analytics for casinos. So it was all about
doing complex data analytics on casinos and that's a really strange field to be involved in
because their primary product in practice really was helping casino managers rearrange slot machines
on the slot floor. Because apparently if you carefully rearrange the slot machines just
right you can increase your revenue by one percent and if you increase your revenue by one
percent at casinos that turns out to be a lot of money. So I was involved in that and so that's
where I learned data analytics originally. So that work actually I did a lot of data analytics
and visualization and oddly enough that was like back in 2000 and I remember I was actually playing
around with self-organizing maps there and different ways of doing visualization. But
ultimately working for casinos is kind of soul crushing and I just couldn't quite bring myself
to do that anymore. So I looked back to academia and ended up heading off to university to do a
PhD in pure math. So that's where I went and that was in algebra and with topological algebra really
and I also did a bunch of algebraic topology. That was my math background and once I was done
that I wanted something a little bit different. I didn't want to stay in academia and the Tata
Institute here in Canada they're sort of they're a government research institute. They have
government clients who are looking for applied things to some extent but it's a pretty it's a
very small research institute but it's very diverse. So we have people who just do really
pure math stuff and data scientists doing real data science things. I actually joined as a
mathematician and was in the pure math space working there but you know what pure math is hard
and you spend a while beating your head against problems that just don't want to be solved and
then occasionally because we're a small group we'd chat with the other people there and the
data scientists they had they had easy problems. So it was just a chance to try out some problems
that I could at least work on attractively and so I spent a little while doing that and have
now now I guess I'm fully on the data science side and I try and pretend I'm still a
mathematician at heart. I guess you and I guess you and I kind of have that in common like I I
actually started out as a as a as a pure math pure math person. I didn't end up going to graduate
school or PhD in pure math but I think one of the one of the reasons why I stopped doing pure math
was similar similar to your story like I had this feeling that you could spend your entire career
and maybe you would happen on a handful of important problems or problems that would have
impact if you were lucky but you would spend a lot of time working on you know writing papers and
doing work that like was important within the context of the field but like it would be difficult
to have especially in pure math would be difficult to have practical practical impact in the world
whereas like when I first got exposure to data science problems and data problems I had this
palpable feeling of like oh there's all these problems that need to be solved and I can go and
do something it's very practical and like it has impact on it has impact uh you know and all these
different all these different ways so I ended up a little bit in data science as as an accident but
it sounds like your your path was a little bit a little bit a little bit similar so not to knock
on pure math like the world needs pure mathematicians like you know we need you know we
need cryptography and all like you know to keep our our system safe and all those things and all
that comes out of pure mathematics um but um you know I I also found that there's way people that
are way smarter than I am working on doing pure math research and so when once I observed like
some of those you know really uh incredibly um super genius pure math people who are just so far
out ahead of me I'm like I just don't think I can uh I don't think I can I can succeed I can
succeed quite the way I would like in this in this field if that makes sense
yeah no I I think uh it's a it's a very similar sort of story um working in pure math is is
definitely a challenge I mean it's very rewarding and I still love pure math but um
yeah instead of looking for uh low-hanging fruit to try and pick uh it's pretty much just
picking fruit up off the ground in data science there are so many problems and
I some of them are very hard but uh there's just so many to choose from that are just
sitting there waiting to be tried uh whereas you know math has many thousands of years of
people hammering away at these problems the easy ones have been found although now you can just
tell AI to do a breakthrough yeah yeah I mean math is certainly one of the fields that I think is
going to change the most with AI I I think that's going to be a really interesting change to see
happening over the next several years is it common for the pure math people to collaborate
with the data science people so I think this is one of the places where the Tutte Institute is
pretty special uh in that it is a place where that happens um we we do have like people like myself I
I came from the pure math side and ended up working in data science but also you know we've got others
who kind of dip back and forth between between each side as it goes and as I said it's a relatively
small research institute we don't have that many people so everyone talks to everyone else
and you know if you can if you can take a data science problem and turn it into a pure math
problem it's not that hard to get the pure math people working on it and and uh as we said yeah
there are people a lot smarter in the pure math realm working on these things so if you can turn
your problem into something that they will want to chew on then you can get a lot of talent
working on a problem for you so but I I think it's I haven't seen it as much uh in in other places to
have quite the same degree of interplay between the the very applied and the pure math side
yeah I mean it sounds like a really kind of serendipitous setup to be able to straddle both
uh parts um I know Hadley mentioned AI a little bit yeah I'm curious how it's affected has it
changed the way you approach your data science work or your math work? Oh caveat and say not
really not yet um but that's mostly because I'm still really trying to figure out how best to use
it so it hasn't changed my work because I'm still playing with it uh I don't think I've settled on
how best to make it fit because there are like it's very powerful it is done I've certainly
been working with it playing with it and learning a lot and it it certainly has helped but I don't
think I have a settled workflow or decision about exactly where it fits. I'm curious about the ways
you've been sort of like experimenting with it or trying it like what what does that look like?
Uh so one of the easy ones is in software development and coding um it's it's just uh
that some of the latest models are remarkably good at that and that has been just an interesting
learning curve to understand how much it can do and also trying to learn what it what it can't do
so well but that's just sitting at loose on uh coding projects and seeing what happens uh or
just getting like minor help but otherwise I've mostly been using it as a way to just
uh I guess it's a rubber duck to talk to um I'll talk to the AI and throw out some ideas of of
directions I'm interested in going and it throws back a bunch of ideas and they're not always great
but they're not bad it's it's a useful just sounding board um to explore ideas. I mean I take
I certainly take anything that it says says or does with a grain of salt um but um I I mostly
use it as a as a tool to to clarify my clarify my thinking or or like help me like what are
questions that I should be asking like is there something that I might be missing here and so
I think in terms of like helping you think laterally or like maybe look at a look at
something from a different perspective it can be it can be really really helpful for that um
unfortunately you know even the latest generation of models like have seem to have like a cognitive
bias where they're inclined to like say that they're inclined to say that whatever you ask
them about like they'll they're inclined to agree with you and tell you that you have a good idea
even still and that was like always the always the joke early on with like the sycophancy and like
essentially glazing your glazing your ideas um and so for that reason like I I even if the AI
AI appears to agree with what I say or say yeah that's a great idea um I'm like is it though
really and so sometimes a gentle pushback say like you just you can say like is it though really like
let's be critical you're not going to hurt my feelings and it will actually have some criticisms
that it withheld in the first go around because it was worried about worried about hurting your
feelings I think worried is giving a little bit too much credit but um my uh my go-to uh approach
for that is I find it's useful for me to if I'll I'll write up an idea it's just a little markdown
document sketch something um upload that and say I I uh got this uh suggestion from someone I think
it's not very good I think it has real problems can you explain what's wrong with it and uh then
it tries to agree with you and tell you how bad it is um which is which is great because that's
what I actually want since uh Leland's also from New Zealand I can share my pet theory that the
problem is that too much of the reinforcement learning is trained on Americans who like to be
sucked up sucked up to more than like New Zealanders so I think if they had New Zealanders
do more of that there would be like less sucking up and more uh brutal honesty I think that's a
good plan do you are New Zealanders brutally honest is that a not brutally I'm more blunt
than Americans yeah there's there's a great there's like a really great book that I recommend
to everyone called called the culture map um that's basically about like the the way like the
different working styles obviously it's like every individual is different but like in generality like
the the the sort of median working style of different countries and and cultures and Americans
notably um have a hard time delivering critical feedback without wrapping it in in a sugar coating
and this is extremely confusing for like other cultures that are used to receiving more blunt
critical feedback like without so you might say like you know here's some good things but then
here's the one piece of criticism that I want to land in this conversation and so if you're not
used to you know that sugar coating of of criticisms then you might hear like oh three
compliments and then one one uh one criticism but like the purpose of the conversation for an
American working workplace is to deliver that one piece of critical feedback like without being too
offensive that reminds me of this blog post from um Kieran Healy Kieran Healy which is like this
about academic feedback and like how US grad students should interpret what faculty trained
in the UK say like yeah like if they say that's not bad the US student hears that's poor but what
the faculty member actually meant is like that's good or if you say I am confused the US PhD student
thinks means that means I am confused but what the faculty member actually meant to say actually
meant to convey is you are an idiot I just and I just thought it was like hilarious and I like
read this like as I was like starting to advise my my first like US PhD students I was like wow
these PhD students are probably really confused by the feedback that I am giving them because
they're hearing it very differently to how I have it I like the idea of pretending like you found
your idea though somewhere and you you're needing help roasting it I feel like yeah yeah I think you
have to disown your idea a little bit to get them to be honest about it yeah and Wes I know you were
feeding a lot of don't you you follow a an approach pretty commonly of feeding one thing's
plan or advice into another thing is that right like you have codex review clod or vice versa
yeah I have like a pretty like a pretty systematic adversarial review pipeline for for everything I
everything I do and in particular I don't whenever I present something for review by a
adversarial in the sense that like you you give something you provide a piece of like a
specification or something for review by another like a fresh agent session that has no prior
knowledge of what you're working on and you don't tell them you don't tell the agent like you know
you don't tell the agent that that you wrote it just like here is a plan that was written by
another agent and and so like without any context and just ask for critical feedback like I think
you could even say like I think there's things wrong with it like find what the things wrong
with it are in the software engineering community there's this very alluring idea of of the dark
factory like this idea of like being able to produce things with AI like without any without
much human intervention basically using like feedback loops of adversarial agents like
one agent writes the specification other agents review one agent implements like other agents
verify but I I you know I'm more of like the human assisted factory type of mindset like
the clankers as we call them are still doing the doing the work but but we need to be in the loop
to provide judgment and and steering and I think without that like you get you get slop out on on
the other end and so I think early on in my my journey building software and tools and systems
with with with AI I there were times when I delegated a little too much to the to the agents
and was surprised to see that what came out on the other end wasn't very good and so finding the
right like striking the right balance of like you know not letting them run with it too much and
and certainly like adversarial feedback I think helps a lot but but I think unfortunately like
they they can't be given too much you know you can't delegate your taste to the to them like
taste is provided by humans and um it's it's it's unfortunate because everyone is really hoping
desperately that they can you know write a prompt and step back from the computer and go you know
have a beer or go for a walk or something and come back to like something that is good but
in my experience like that almost never happens and so like if you want it to be good like you
know you need to be a maniac about the details and really um engaged with like the the fine details
of what what you want the agents to produce for you it seems like two one almost like one theme
with a lot of your tools and the more applied data science work is it is it is does seem very
human-centric like even like the that you map and things like this commonly end in a visualization
like it does seem like one thread is that a lot of your work has been really useful for
people to like dig around and make sense of things and visualize yeah i i mean i guess if
there's one one theme in my work it was that when i started very early in data analytics and data
science obviously the first big problem that you you come across is you get data and now you have
to do all the data cleaning and eda work and all this stuff to sort through that and then you can
finally get around to the like supervised machine learning once you've got it sorted
and i guess i never got past the first part uh i'm still trying to trying to build the tools to
to do uh that eda framework uh to do exploratory data analysis and i guess my focus has been on
the fact that i feel like we're lacking in tools for eda on unstructured data like i think i think
you know tabular data is something for which we have amazing tools and uh hadley and west have
both written plenty of amazing tools for doing great eda on tabular data but when you have a
giant pile of documents or images or videos or a mixture of all three how do you work out what's
in that data set and how do you explore it in a meaningful way and i don't i'm like i think i
think the answer is you're going to need to feed that to a human somehow because i don't think an
ai can just have all the answers because of exactly as west was saying it's about taste like
you have to have some i have some sense of what i'm looking to find or know more about and it's
very hard for ai right now to to do that but you know what's the channels via which i can get the
information about that data set into my brain and visualization is one of the strongest ones
but you know other means of building summarizations that's where a lot of the clustering
and things like that come in as well i just want to find ways to condense and extract information
to just allow someone to explore a data set better and that's that's the through line of
of all the various kinds of tools i've i've been building that's just i want to help people
understand their data yeah yeah it's so interesting and i guess even the art
uh behind you really speaks to that that it's like scientists and it's it's people looking for
illegal gold mining but also artists um have found found use for this of almost taking
data in the world or like relationships and even rendering it like artistically
as like a work of art on its own is i think a really powerful testament to that like the taste
and an aesthetic aspect of it yeah yeah so so the work behind me is by an artist
Rafik Anadol uh who does a lot of digital art uh he uses umap in some of his work he uses a lot
of ai tools and a bunch of his work but he's i think his his tagline is he wants to use data
as a pigment for generating art data is his paintbrush and i i think that's that's an
intriguing uh view on this i think there's a lot you can do with uh a lot of modern tools
ai tools and otherwise for actually generating art and i don't mean in the the
actually generating art. And I don't mean in the sense where you write a prompt and it
generates a picture for you, but more as a tool to do more interesting things.
There was a great artist, Kyle McDonald, who I've had back and forth with a couple of times.
He's reached out and one of his projects was just analyzing whale song for a physical art
installation that was going to get built, but it was just in the background of the analysis.
He was using UMAP for some things and so I had some back and forth with him about that.
Fancy tooling in data science was not showing up necessarily in the end product art,
but it's a useful tool in the building structure.
It's a useful tool in the building structure that goes into producing the art.
And I mean, I think there's a lot of processing like that, that I think...
These tools have a lot of ways they can be used that aren't obvious.
And the map, the idea of the map is such a powerful metaphor, and people love to look
at maps.
Not just of physical things, but it'd be like maps of the internet, and maps of music, and
it's...
Yeah, those spatial connections are something that feels like humans just have some in-built
desire to think about and look at and experience.
Yeah, spatially navigating data is a magical thing if you can make it happen, and it's
challenging to make it happen well, it turns out.
I mean, I wrote UMAP quite some time ago.
I still think there's better algorithms out there, and that's one of the things that I'm
busy working on now, is just trying to understand better how this actually should work, because
I think there's more answers out there.
And I think managing to make data spatial and the geometry of data is actually a fundamental
thing in all these AI representations, like the neural embedding models and these things.
That's really about the interrelationships and geometry of the data, and so it's about
geometry and topology of information.
And so everything is spatial for the internals of the AI, and I think if we can make that
interpretable to people, that will be very, very helpful.
And you mentioned neural embedding models, could you break that down for someone who
maybe doesn't...
Might interact with AI like Claude, but is less in the guts of it?
Okay, I'll see what I can do.
So if you're interacting with Claude, you have your prompt that you send it, and it
basically does some processing, but it's processing stuff in pure numbers, eventually, as it's
shoving it all through the neural network.
And you can take an individual layer of that neural network and pull out the numbers that
it has for processing a single thing.
And that's a vector of numbers.
And it turns out that these vectors of numbers actually organize themselves in space.
In a meaningful way.
And so instead of handing something in to Claude to get a textual response out, there
are other models that are designed specifically for I'm gonna hand some text in, or I'm gonna
hand an image in, and it's just gonna spit out the vector of numbers associated to that.
And though the interrelationships between those vectors are meaningful on a semantic
level, the vectors will be similar, close to each other in space, if the semantics of
the text was similar.
And so this is a very powerful way of dealing with these things.
But now we're trying to do geometry in very high dimensional spaces, because these vectors
that they spit out, they're not nice ones you can plot easily.
They're in usually, these days, thousands of dimensions.
And so the geometry of high dimensional space turns out to be very important if we want
to understand what's going on inside the neural networks.
That's a fun challenge that I enjoy trying to work on, because I think it's almost impossible
for people to have good intuitions for what geometry in high dimensional space looks like.
If you want, I can give you a slew of examples for how to break your intuition.
I'm open to it.
I mean, when you mentioned high dimensional geometry, I was like, I have no idea how we'll
unpack that.
So if you have any examples, I'm all ears.
Yeah.
Okay.
So if I make a sphere, if I draw a circle and then draw a box around it, the sphere
mostly fills the box.
If I, and the circle mostly fills the box.
If I do a sphere and draw a cube around it, there's slightly more space in the corners
of the cube.
If I just keep going up in dimensions, eventually the sphere contains almost no volume whatsoever
and all the volume lives in the corners of the box.
So somehow everything lives in the corners.
So another way to think about it, I can take a circle and draw a little tiny thin shell
around it.
What's the area of the circle compared to the area of the shell?
Well, I mean, it's almost entirely circle.
I can do a ball and make a thin candy coating, the rind around an orange.
The orange contains most of the meat.
The rind is just this little thin bit.
But no matter how thin you make that thin bit, there's a high enough dimension that
more volume lives in the rind of the orange than inside the orange itself.
So suddenly everything is living on the surface of these spheres.
What's another one?
If you take a sphere, ball, and draw a band around the equator, what height of band do
you need to cover 99% of the surface area of the ball?
In what we're used to, you have to cover, it's mostly the height of the ball.
In high dimensions, that value goes to almost zero.
Almost all the surface area of a ball in high dimensions lives on the equator.
But I said the equator.
Any rotation will do.
So any equator you draw around the ball contains most of the surface area of the ball.
It's very hard to conceptualize all of that.
And this is the problem.
It behaves, high dimensional spaces just behave in ways that are run entirely counter to our
intuitions about how this should work.
Yeah.
I appreciate you taking a stab at that because I think that it's, I don't know, it seems
important if like high dimensional geometry seems like a really useful, fruitful area.
And it sounds like you're really aimed at it.
I feel like it's such a helpful kind of like way to prime the pump on how this behaves.
If everything's in the rind of the orange, it's such a helpful analogy for at least trying
to like glimpse what these problems might kind of like feel like to someone.
And you're saying that these are important because these are like, like UMAP essentially
is for high dimensional problems where you have a lot of like measurements per observation.
And this space is just kind of like a weird space.
Yeah.
Your intuitions for how it should behave are all based on, you know, your everyday experience,
which is in a like three dimensional world.
And if those intuitions are just really wrong, it turns out for these problems.
And so it's very easy to design algorithms and work with the data thinking you know how
it should behave.
And it turns out it doesn't.
So, you know, the examples I was trying to give, they're less, they're mostly just to
try and demonstrate that you just shouldn't trust any of your intuitions because your
intuitions are probably wrong.
And you're going to have to do the hard work of really reasoning through very carefully
rather than just basing everything on, oh, yeah, you know, everything should behave this
way.
It makes sense.
Well, not in high dimensional data, unfortunately.
I guess maybe that leads us into, I'd be curious, like some of the things you're working on
now.
I know I saw a little bit about evoke.
Yeah.
So, evoke is for embedding vector oriented clustering.
And the goal there is that essentially these neural embedding vectors are how a lot of
our data is represented now.
There's still always going to be lots of tabular data.
But for all the things, as I said, like documents, text, video, audio, images, the way people
represent those now is with these neural embedding vectors because you can do lots of machine
learning with them.
But now we need ways to work with those.
So, it's a clustering algorithm designed specifically with that kind of high dimensional data in
mind to be as fast as possible and just get you to some decent clustering results quickly.
Because it's, again, for that exploratory data analysis view, you want quick turnaround.
You want to be able to do something and explore it and go, oh, okay, I learned something and
then pivot to the next experiment and the next experiment, tweak some parameters and
just keep playing around in an experimental fashion.
So, it's a clustering algorithm for high dimensional embedding vectors designed for that kind of
exploratory quick turnaround.
And you're working with data scientists at the Tutte Institute on it?
What does that look like?
That one's primarily my project.
I'm working with some people on a different project called Toponomy.
That's from the Greek.
It's the idea of naming places.
So, this is very much, as Hadley was saying, that spatial sense and the sense of a map
is pretty important.
But a map is meaningful when you can put some place names on it.
And so, if the map is of an information space generated from the space of all these documents
about something, how do I put meaningful names at many different resolutions on that map?
And so, with that one, LLMs and AI is playing a big role because they're, turns out, really
good at language.
But a lot of it comes down to just managing to do things like provide that multi-resolution
clustering and how do I extract the right information to feed an LLM to have it give
a good name to this thing?
So, it's kind of related to topic modeling, but its goal is to be a little bit richer.
And ideally, topic modeling for whatever you can turn into embedding vectors.
So, you might notice a theme.
I just assume these days that lots of stuff is going to be turned into these embedding
vectors.
And then, how do I look at or explore that space of data?
That made me realize there's a little project that I've been working on that I started to
use embeddings for.
So, at Posit, we do these monthly Ask Me Anythings where anyone in the company can ask questions
of leadership.
And so, now we have this kind of database of questions and answers.
And of course, people ask the same question, but there's no great way to say, here's all
the similar questions that you asked in the past.
And so, I was like, okay, well, I can at least do some related.
When I look at one question, show me the related question.
So, I was like, well, that's easy to do now.
Just do some embeddings and then find the ones that are closest.
But that's making me think it would be great to have a map of this as well, so you can
kind of see these are the sort of clusters that questions tend to come into.
And that's exactly your example of, here's an unstructured data analysis, where we 100%
know that there's some really rich structure here, but how do you quickly figure that out
and iterate and then give it to people in a way that they can understand?
Yeah.
It sounds like it's probably a fascinating dataset.
There are probably some really tight clusters where people keep asking almost the same question.
And then there's probably some interesting clusters where it's diffuse and it's lots
of people asking variations of the same question, but heading in all sorts of different directions.
I mean, there's so much you could learn and explore in that sort of data.
And so, yeah, this is the tooling that I want to try and build is how to explore when it's
not a nice tabular dataset anymore.
Yeah.
And also accepting that any 2D rendering is going to be a massive simplification of reality.
And you probably don't just want one, but you want a selection that maybe people can
iterate through.
But then how do you help them find the right one for their needs?
And yeah, lots of interesting questions.
Yeah.
I mean, my mental model of these things, especially the 2D map views, is that it's a lens through
which you're viewing the data and it's deliberately providing a distortion.
I mean, a lens is not very useful unless you want a microscope lens that will show you
detail or a telescope lens that'll take in a lot of information and condense it down.
Whatever you do, you're going to distort the data.
So you just want to have as many different lenses through which you can look at the data.
And so you just want to swap between lenses so you get these different views.
And that's, I think, the best way you can get to data understanding.
Because, yeah, I mean, to bring it back to maps again, the classic example of this is
the London tube map, which fundamentally distorts distance but gives you a much better understanding
of the network.
You don't want multiple views like that of your data.
Yeah.
And if you've ever looked at the London tube map rendered onto an actual geographic map,
it's a mess and hard to make any sense of.
But at least you understand how far apart some of the stations are, which is not at
all obvious from the classic map.
And these are the challenges.
You want to present different views for different tasks.
I did cognitive psychology and a little neuroscience, and that does remind me of brain anatomy,
where we have names for a lot of the different parts of the brain and how they connect to
each other.
But obviously, all our brains are different, even the shape of various places.
So somehow we agreed upon these labels, but also in research, you have to figure out how
to mash them onto each other, register it onto a canonical brain.
And it is interesting that need to categorize the parts, but also sometimes map them onto
each other and what you keep and what you lose in the process.
Yeah.
I mean, it's the constant conflict between the desire to understand it in the continuous
space and our constant desire to be able to categorize.
These are always in conflict, but they're both useful and you've got to be able to somehow
pivot between those two instincts that I think we have.
That also reminds me of Procrustes analysis, which I kind of love because it's so called
because this Greek myth of Procrustes, who is like a smith who used his hammer to make
people fit the shape of his bed exactly.
And that's kind of like what you're doing in this brain, you're just hammering bits
to make it fit this reference brain.
I was curious.
Do you drive anyone crazy from your desire to categorize and dimensionality reduce?
Is there anyone who's like, you got to stop clustering things?
So my colleagues are all great and they're mostly the people I talk to.
So I don't have that problem.
One of the advantages of working at the Institute, as I said, I'm from the pure math side.
There are the data science people who get more and more applied.
And so generally speaking, they're the people talking to the frontline analysts actually
doing the work.
So I want that one level of remove where the problems get abstracted a little bit away
to something I can work on.
So I guess that saves me from having to be told that.
I'm sure they are sick of being told that maps or clusters or summarizations like this
are the answer.
I mean, again, it's an answer.
It's what I've got.
It's the hammer.
I'll throw at things, but I'm not going to pretend that it's the answer.
It's just the best tools I have at hand at the moment.
If somebody can come up with some better tools, I'll be more than happy to start reaching
out in that direction.
Do you see those like tendencies playing out in your personal life as well?
Are there like households or tasks that you want to map?
No, actually.
My work and personal life manages to stay reasonably separate.
So I think that one's a good one.
I'm glad it stays that way.
Like household chores, you're not like, this is a high dimensional space.
We got to reduce it.
No, no, no.
At some point, I just want to get things done.
Or are you the person who wants things to be perfectly arranged in the dishwasher for
maximum packing efficiency?
Yeah.
So, no, it turns out that's not me.
I think that's a thing that people expect in some ways, maybe from a mathematician,
is like the desire for organization.
And I drive my wife crazy because she's a list maker.
She always wants to make lists, to-do lists, any lists to check things off.
And I don't, and she gets very frustrated with me because I'm not organized and making
lists and keeping everything neatly categorized.
She's probably the one more likely to rearrange things in the dishwasher than I am to do better
So, yeah, oddly enough, I'm on the opposite of the stereotype, I guess.
I saw that you mentioned like imposter syndrome that even, I mean, I would say you like have
an incredible list of accomplishments and I would say like dancing in pure mathematics
and in data science is a pretty astounding feat.
I was really surprised to see you mention that you experienced imposter syndrome in
some of the places.
I think that's really common.
But I'm curious if you could say a bit about that piece.
Sure.
Well, I mean, one example you said is I'm in pure math and data science, but that mostly
means I feel like I'm failing to keep up with the pure math.
Like I go to math conferences and it's a struggle because there are people doing amazing things
that I can barely wrap my head around.
And then in data science, I'm a dilettante, dabbling in data science.
I'm not a data science expert and I don't really know what I'm doing.
So I feel out of place in both worlds.
I have ended up writing software tools in Python, but I'm certainly not a software engineer
and I don't really feel like one.
And I constantly feel like I don't know what I'm doing as far as software engineering goes.
I'm doing the best I can and it seems to be working, but this is an ongoing thing.
I constantly feel a little bit out of place.
And so, yeah, imposter syndrome is certainly something that I do try to deal with.
And so mostly my way to deal with that is to just try and keep my head down and focused on
what I'm doing and try not to worry about how it fits into everything else.
Which, as you mentioned, it happens to show up in lots of places.
So I guess I get people reaching out and talking about it in these ways, but I try
and keep my head down because otherwise I feel like I mostly don't know anything about anything
and I'm just doing the best I can.
Yeah, I'd imagine when you're straddling, it sounds like when you're straddling two
areas, that's like a big challenge of just the net you've cast.
But I don't know.
It's so interesting to hear because I feel like it's such a useful spot to be in,
like that kind of interdisciplinary zone.
I'm a huge fan of interdisciplinary work.
I think I really feel like that's where a lot of really useful things happen.
When different things end up mixing together, that's when interesting things happen.
And so I'm happy to be able to be in this interdisciplinary spot.
As I said, I feel like that's one of the real strengths of the TUT Institute,
the Research Institute, is that we have a bunch of this interdisciplinary.
And I mean, to some people, I guess it's not very interdisciplinary because it's like math
and computer science and data science, and maybe those are all the same as far as some
people are concerned.
But they're wildly different to people working in those fields.
I would love to see more, more interdisciplinary work.
I was curious too, like in the, this is a bit of a tangent, but I noticed like on the
topic of sort of doing programming and pure math, I noticed, are you, you're working on
a Rust library now too, is that?
Who isn't working on a Rust library?
So actually that one is, I said I needed projects so I could try out AI and learn how good it
is at programming.
So that was one of my AI projects.
I am not Rust fluent at all, but I had a Python library for approximate nearest neighbor search
that made use of the number library, which JIT compiles the Python down to LLVM machine
code.
So it actually runs surprisingly fast, even though it's pure Python.
And so I was just curious, like this seemed like a good task for AI models.
Rewrite this library in Rust, because you should be able to make it go faster.
And so what I've just put up on GitHub is the final output, but it took way, way longer
than I expected.
I started on this well over a year ago.
And the models back then, I think it was like Opus 4.5 with Claude I started out with.
It could not do it.
It wrote a Rust version of the library and it did function eventually, but there was
a lot of back and forth with the model saying, this is great, but please run the benchmark
again, because it's still slower than the Python.
And it took a long time.
And so I think only the latest models have actually gotten to a point where it could
make it run faster than Python code.
Well, because it was already being just in time compiled by number, right?
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
It's fast Python code, but still, I feel like a Rust native implementation specialized
should be able to get at least as performant as that.
And so it turns out that this is a challenge for the model.
So this was a learning experience for me to learn how good are the models at this.
And so I think they've gotten there in as much as I've produced it, it's slightly
faster than the Python in a number of ways.
So this is good.
It's not as flexible, but that's your trade-off.
But that was me having a learning curve and an excuse to play around with the models.
Yeah, it's such an interesting experiment.
And I was curious as I saw it, the kind of like Rust library standing out to what's
this point, it seems like a really nice testing ground to see.
Do you, coming out of it, did you, do you feel like, did you learn anything useful for,
like that you took out of it for working with AI, like coding with AI or?
Yeah, I think the thing that really made it work was that there was a very targeted goal
and I could actually have it write tests and benchmarks.
I had test suites in the pipe.
So there was, this was very much what Wes was talking about.
If you can make it very specific, you can, you can have it run away and do a bunch of
stuff.
But it needed the specificity and it needed the, the ability to just go back and forth
and benchmark against the Python code and have it run it itself and go, Oh yeah, no,
you're right.
It is still slower.
That was kind of critical to manage for me to make it work.
So I guess that that was one of the big takeaways for me is I, if I, if I want to actually have
a large scale project, because this was, as opposed to just editing what's there a
little bit, it needs to be able to be very specific.
And I need to be able to frame everything that it needs to be able to do with a great
deal of specificity.
Do you have any new Rust libraries you'll be making or next experiments?
Ah, I don't know.
I mean, I guess in theory I should, I should see if it can port UMAP to Rust.
I'm sure people have already done this.
Um, but I mean, from the point of view of, of running the experiment to see what it can
do, that would be, that would be a, uh, an interesting challenge.
Um, I don't know how much difference that'll make.
I, yeah, still, still learning Rust really myself that the LLMs are good at it though.
I don't, you know, one last thing I wanted to bring up to make sure to bring up is, um,
I, I heard in an interview with, um, Vincent Vormerdam that you did, he, he brought up
a really interesting quote that I think Hadley gave at some point, um, which was essentially
that algorithms can scale, but they often don't surprise you.
Uh, does this sound familiar Hadley?
Yeah, this was my, always my pitch for why you needed visualization and modeling like
visualization doesn't scale because a human's got to look at it, but it can surprise you.
And models like every model makes some assumptions and they can never question those
assumptions.
So at some level it can't surprise you.
Uh, although now I have to maybe reconsider that if we think of LLMs as being a model,
since they certainly like surprise us all the time in interesting ways.
Different sense of model though, because I mean, it's, it's very much closer to a visualization
and that it's distilling something out to a summary that you still have to feed through
a human.
So I'd put it in the same class as visualization.
It's something you're feeding to, to a human.
And that's the part that surprises you.
I love that quote.
I think it's fabulous.
I reuse it all the time because it is very much, I think the motivation for the kind
of exploratory work that, that I'm interested in.
I want the thing that will surprise people.
That's the most important part, um, because I, so I'm interested in helping people ask
better questions rather than finding answers.
Um, that's, I guess my.
So, I'm interested in helping people ask better questions rather than finding answers.
That's, I guess, my would-be quote. Because I think there are lots of ways to squeeze data
and get answers. But I think knowing what question you should be asking is a much harder problem
these days. Yeah, and I guess that goes back,
too, to your focus on the EDA stage. Essentially, like, what question should I ask?
Feeling like you're always at that early stage, trying to sort out the questions.
Yeah. My colleague, John Healy, his go-to quote is just, look at your data.
That's all he ever says. And he means that in the broadest possible sense of look at your data.
Open it up in Excel and stare at lines in a spreadsheet. Whatever. Just actually look at
what's in your data. I've seen him working with analysts who bring a data set. And he'll ask a
bunch of questions about, well, what's true of this data? What do you at least know about it?
Because whatever they say is true of the data, it's almost always a thing that he will then
go and falsify by going through the data. No, that, in fact, is false. There are negative values
in here. I'm sorry, but the timestamps are not contiguous and not they're duplicated in some
places or whatever. Whatever assumptions people make about their data turn out not to be true.
And so, that's a lot of the motivation for my desire to just try and ask better questions
is people assume they know what's in data and it is almost never true. And you just need to
be able to get people to a point where they can realize that for themselves.
It seems like incredible advice. And especially in the AI era too, with evals, I guess that
has surfaced with people like Hamel, Hussein mentioning, you could put a number on it,
but you should probably also look at what's going on and get close to examples and outputs
to see if what you're measuring is even sort of what you want. Yeah, it's honestly so fascinating
to hear about your path through pure mathematics and data science and to see these tools and
algorithms like UMAP just cut across so many areas. Yeah, I think I'll be thinking about
for a while also just the exploratory nature of it and how we could live and
we could drill into exploration way more than maybe we expect. Any parting words?
Look at your data. Ask better questions.
Yep, Leland, thanks for coming on and great seeing you.
Yeah, thanks so much for having me on. I really enjoyed it.
Yeah, thanks, Steven.
Thanks for coming on.
The Test Set is a production of PositPBC, an open source and enterprise tooling data
science software company. This episode was produced in collaboration with creative studio
Agi. For more episodes, visit thetestset.co or find us on your favorite podcast platform.